<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="info"
     docName="draft-schemacommons-acpm-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     submissionType="independent"
     xml:lang="en"
     version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="ACPM">Agent Capability and Profile Model (ACPM)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schemacommons-acpm-00"/>

    <author initials="B." surname="van Bussel" fullname="Bob van Bussel">
      <organization>Observalytics SL</organization>
      <address>
        <email>bob@observalytics.com</email>
        <uri>https://github.com/Observalytics-SL</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2026" month="June" day="25"/>
    <area>ART</area>

    <keyword>AI agents</keyword>
    <keyword>capability profile</keyword>
    <keyword>trust and attestation</keyword>
    <keyword>cost comparison</keyword>
    <keyword>service level agreement</keyword>
    <keyword>interoperability</keyword>
    <keyword>JSON Schema</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        The Agent Capability and Profile Model (ACPM) is an open, vendor-neutral
        specification for describing what an artificial intelligence (AI) agent,
        the platform that runs it, a tool it calls, or the underlying large
        language model (LLM) actually offers, independent of how that subject is
        run or discovered.  An ACPM document, called a capability profile,
        declares a subject's identity, a dot-namespaced list of supported
        capabilities together with a support level, an inventory of tool
        protocols, models, and memory backends, a trust and attestation posture,
        a cost structure, service-level commitments, structured delegation rules
        governing inbound and outbound work handoff, and a compliance posture.
      </t>
      <t>
        ACPM profiles are designed to cross-reference agent definitions and
        registry entries defined by other Schema Commons standards, and to be
        consumed by registries, marketplaces, and orchestrators that need to
        compare capabilities, gate on trust, and reason about cost and service
        levels without bespoke per-vendor parsing.  This document describes the
        ACPM data model, field semantics, conformance levels, and the
        relationship of ACPM's trust and signature fields to actual
        verification, which ACPM deliberately does not itself perform.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        As of mid-2026, the AI agent ecosystem has converged on two adjacent
        but distinct interoperability problems.  The first is how to express a
        portable, runnable agent definition so that an agent built on one
        runtime can be executed on another; this is the problem the
        Autonomous Agent Interchange Format (AAIF) <xref target="SC-006"/>
        addresses.  The second is
        how to discover an agent within a registry or marketplace; this is the
        problem the Agent Registry (AREG) addresses.  Neither problem
        encompasses a third, equally common need: describing, comparing, and
        reasoning about what an agent, the platform running it, the tools it
        calls, or the underlying model actually offers.
      </t>
      <t>
        Today this information is scattered across marketing pages, ad hoc
        vendor-specific JSON, ASCII tables in README files, and human-readable
        documentation that changes shape from vendor to vendor.  There is no
        canonical way to ask, in a machine-checkable way, whether a given
        subject supports a particular capability and at what fidelity, what
        evidence backs a trust claim about that subject, what it costs to use,
        what service level applies, or under what conditions it may delegate
        work to, or accept delegated work from, another subject.  Registries
        and orchestrators that need this information today either write
        bespoke parsers per vendor or forgo capability, trust, and cost
        comparison entirely.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document specifies the Agent Capability and Profile Model (ACPM),
        a portable, vendor-neutral format for a capability profile: a
        standalone description of what a subject offers.  ACPM is deliberately
        scoped to be orthogonal to, and composable with, both the runnable
        agent definition problem and the registry discovery problem; it does
        not replace either.
      </t>

      <section anchor="requirements-language" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
          The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and
          "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
          when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="scope" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Scope</name>
        <t>
          ACPM is in scope for: subject identity (agent, platform, tool, or
          model); declared capability support levels using a dot-namespaced
          vocabulary; tool-invocation protocol, model, and memory-backend
          inventories; trust level and attestation evidence; sandboxing
          characteristics; pricing model and unit cost; service-level
          commitments; structured rules governing delegation of work between
          profiled subjects; compliance posture (data residency,
          certifications, personally identifiable information handling); and
          profile provenance.
        </t>
        <t>
          ACPM is out of scope for: the execution loop of the profiled subject;
          registry listing and discovery mechanics; and cryptographic
          enforcement or verification of any claim a profile makes.  ACPM
          specifies the shape of a trust or signature claim; verifying that
          claim is the responsibility of the system consuming the profile.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="terminology" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>ACPM document / profile</dt>
        <dd>
          A JSON instance conforming to the ACPM profile schema.
        </dd>
        <dt>Subject</dt>
        <dd>
          The agent, platform, tool, or model that a profile describes.
        </dd>
        <dt>Capability</dt>
        <dd>
          A dot-namespaced runtime feature string a subject may offer, paired
          with a declared support level.
        </dd>
        <dt>Producer</dt>
        <dd>
          Software or a person that publishes an ACPM profile.
        </dd>
        <dt>Consumer</dt>
        <dd>
          Software that reads an ACPM profile to make a capability-matching,
          trust-gating, cost, or service-level decision.
        </dd>
        <dt>Conformance level</dt>
        <dd>
          One of the five cumulative conformance levels defined in
          <xref target="conformance"/> that a profile satisfies.
        </dd>
        <dt>Condition</dt>
        <dd>
          The structured-or-string gating type used in delegation rules,
          reused without modification from the Autonomous Agent Interchange
          Format.  See <xref target="conditions"/>.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="design-principles" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Design Principles</name>
      <t>ACPM is built on six design principles:</t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
        <li>
          <strong>Claims, not contracts.</strong>  A profile states what the
          subject claims to offer.  ACPM does not itself verify any claim; a
          Consumer that requires assurance <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> perform its own
          verification.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Vocabulary-compatible with AAIF.</strong>  Capability
          identifiers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use the same dot-namespaced strings
          as the Autonomous Agent Interchange Format's required-capability
          vocabulary, so an agent's declared needs and a profile's declared
          offerings can be compared directly.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Composable, not coupled.</strong>  ACPM cross-references
          agent definitions and registry entries by identifier reference; it
          does not import or extend their schemas, so each specification can
          evolve independently.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Comparable by construction.</strong>  Every offer-side
          concept — capability support, trust level, cost, service level —
          uses a closed, ordered, or structured vocabulary rather than free
          text, so two profiles can be diffed or ranked mechanically.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Strict by default, extensible at the edges.</strong>  Every
          object disallows additional properties, with a reserved
          extension-key namespace at the document root for forward
          compatibility and vendor metadata.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Honest about enforceability.</strong>  Fields describing
          trust, attestation, and signature are explicitly documented as
          advisory unless a Consumer independently verifies them.  This
          specification does not imply a cryptographic guarantee it does not
          provide.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="document-structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>ACPM Document Structure</name>
      <t>
        An ACPM profile is a JSON object validated against the ACPM profile
        schema (JSON Schema draft 2020-12 <xref target="JSON-SCHEMA"/>).  The
        minimum conformant document requires only two top-level fields:
      </t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
{
  "sc_standard": "SC-014",
  "subject": { "subject_type": "agent", "name": "Example Agent" }
}
]]></artwork>

      <t>
        The full object model is organised as follows:
      </t>

      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
CapabilityProfile (root)
  sc_standard       "SC-014"  (required)
  sc_version        string (semver, default "1.0.0")
  profile_id        string (UUID)
  subject           (required)
    subject_type    agent | platform | tool | model
    name / vendor / version / homepage
    sc_refs[]       cross-references to other Schema Commons documents
  capabilities[]    id / support / version_constraint / notes
  tools[]           protocol / max_concurrent_calls / auth_methods[]
  models[]          provider / model_id / context_window / modalities[]
  memory[]          backend / scopes[]
  trust
    level       untrusted | sandboxed | verified | attested | enterprise
    attestation  issuer / method / evidence_url / issued_at / expires_at
    sandbox          isolation / network_egress
  cost_profile
    pricing_model    free | usage_based | subscription | tiered | custom
    currency / unit_cost / free_tier
  sla
    uptime_pct / p50_latency_ms / p99_latency_ms
    support_tier / incident_response
  delegation_rules[]
    direction / target / condition / action
  compliance
    data_residency[] / certifications[] / pii_handling
  provenance
    authored_by / created_at / updated_at / license / signature
]]></artwork>

      <section anchor="subject-fields" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Subject Identity</name>
        <t>
          The subject.subject_type field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of "agent",
          "platform", "tool", or "model", and the subject.name field
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be present.  The subject.sc_refs array carries
          structured cross-references, each an object with a "standard" field
          (a Schema Commons standard code such as "SC-006") and an "id" field
          (an identifier within that standard's own document, such as an AAIF
          agent_id or an Agent Registry (AREG) entry identifier).  These
          references are advisory pointers; ACPM does not require the
          referenced document to exist or be reachable.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="capabilities-section" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Capabilities</name>
        <t>
          Each entry in the capabilities array declares a dot-namespaced
          capability identifier and a support level.  The identifier
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> reuse the vocabulary already established by
          the Autonomous Agent Interchange Format's required-capability field
          (for example, "tool.mcp", "memory.vector", "orchestration.parallel")
          where the underlying concept overlaps, and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> extend
          it with new namespaces such as "vision.*", "audio.*", "reasoning.*",
          "auth.*", or "state.*" for concepts AAIF does not enumerate.
        </t>
        <t>
          The support field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of four values:
          "native" (first-class, fully supported), "emulated" (achieved
          through a workaround or composition of other features), "partial"
          (supported with material limitations that <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
          documented in the notes field), or "none" (explicitly absent).
          Declaring "none" explicitly, rather than omitting the capability
          entirely, allows a Consumer to distinguish "known not supported"
          from "not yet assessed."
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="inventories" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Tool, Model, and Memory Inventories</name>
        <t>
          The tools array enumerates supported tool-invocation protocols
          drawn from the same four-protocol vocabulary as the Autonomous
          Agent Interchange Format: function, MCP <xref target="MCP"/>, HTTP,
          and OpenAPI.  Each entry <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> declare a concurrency
          ceiling and a list of supported authentication methods.
        </t>
        <t>
          The models array enumerates LLMs the subject exposes or routes to
          (or, when subject_type is "model", describes itself), with
          provider, model identifier, context window, maximum output tokens,
          and supported modalities (text, image, audio, video, tool_use).
        </t>
        <t>
          The memory array enumerates supported storage backends and, for
          each, the memory scopes available on it, using the same backend
          and scope vocabularies as the Autonomous Agent Interchange Format's
          memory configuration.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="trust-section" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Trust and Attestation</name>
        <t>
          The trust.level field is an ordered, five-tier claim: "untrusted"
          (no claim verified), "sandboxed" (executes under some isolation
          boundary but claims are otherwise unverified), "verified" (claims
          checked, even if only by self-certification), "attested" (a named
          issuer has produced a dated, linkable attestation), and "enterprise"
          (attested, with organisational accountability typically evidenced
          by populated service-level and compliance fields).
        </t>
        <t>
          A profile <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> declare any trust level without
          external verification; this specification places no technical
          control in front of an inflated claim.  A Consumer that gates a
          decision on trust.level <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> check
          trust.attestation.evidence_url and <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> verify that
          trust.attestation.expires_at, if present, has not passed before
          relying on an "attested" or "enterprise" claim.  See
          <xref target="security"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The trust.sandbox object describes the isolation boundary the
          subject executes within (none, process, container, or virtual
          machine) and its network egress policy (none, allowlist, or full).
          This describes isolation the subject runs under, not isolation
          a Consumer receives when calling the subject remotely; transport
          security remains the Consumer's own responsibility.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="cost-sla-section" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cost Profile and Service Level</name>
        <t>
          The cost_profile object declares a pricing model (free,
          usage_based, subscription, tiered, or custom), a currency, a single
          unit cost (a billing dimension — request, 1000 tokens, minute, or
          run — paired with an amount), and an optional free tier (included
          units per day or month).  A subject with pricing across multiple
          dimensions <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> publish the most comparable
          dimension, or publish one profile per pricing tier.
        </t>
        <t>
          The sla object declares uptime percentage, p50 and p99 latency in
          milliseconds, a support tier (community, standard, premium, or
          enterprise), and an incident-response commitment for Severity 1
          incidents.  These figures <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> represent either
          contractual commitments or observed historical performance; this
          version of ACPM does not yet distinguish the two, which is a known
          limitation.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="delegation-section" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Delegation Rules</name>
        <t>
          The delegation_rules array governs whether the subject may hand
          work to ("outbound") or accept work from ("inbound") another
          profiled subject.  Each rule <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> scope itself to a
          specific counterparty profile, a specific capability, a minimum
          counterparty trust level, and an additional Condition (see
          <xref target="conditions"/>), and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> declare an
          action: "allow", "deny", or "require_approval".  At least one of
          the target fields <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be present per rule, though
          this is authoring guidance rather than a structural requirement, so
          that intentionally broad direction-only rules remain expressible.
        </t>
        <t>
          When a rule's action is "require_approval", a Consumer
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> obtain explicit approval before proceeding with
          the delegated work; treating "require_approval" as equivalent to
          "allow" is a conformance violation.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="compliance-section" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Compliance</name>
        <t>
          The compliance object declares data residency regions (EU, US, UK,
          APAC, or custom), a free-form list of held certifications, and a
          PII-handling mode (none, redact, encrypt, or forbidden).
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="conditions" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Condition Expressions</name>
      <t>
        The delegation_rules[].condition field accepts a Condition value,
        reused without modification from the Autonomous Agent Interchange
        Format.  The structured form (RECOMMENDED) is an object naming an
        expression language and an expression:
      </t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
{ "lang": "cel", "expr": "request.network_egress != 'full'" }
]]></artwork>
      <t>
        Supported languages are jsonpath, jmespath, cel (Common Expression
        Language), jsonlogic, always (constant true), and never (constant
        false).  A bare string is also accepted as a non-deterministic,
        natural-language hint and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be relied upon for
        portable, reproducible gating.
      </t>
      <t>
        A Consumer that supports a declared lang <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> evaluate
        the structured form deterministically.  A Consumer that does not
        support a declared lang <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> treat the rule as
        unsatisfiable-unknown and apply a conservative default — deny for an
        outbound rule, reject for an inbound rule — rather than silently
        treating it as satisfied.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="conformance" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Conformance Levels</name>
      <t>
        ACPM defines five cumulative conformance levels.  As with the
        Autonomous Agent Interchange Format, conformance is self-certified;
        there is no central certifying authority.
      </t>
      <table align="center">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Level</th>
            <th align="left">Requirements</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Basic</td>
            <td>Validates against the profile schema; subject present.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Tooled</td>
            <td>Basic + capabilities array non-empty.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Trusted</td>
            <td>Tooled + trust.level is verified, attested, or enterprise.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Priced</td>
            <td>Trusted + cost_profile present.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Enterprise</td>
            <td>Priced + sla present + compliance present + provenance.signature present.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>
        A profile claiming a given level satisfies every predicate of all
        lower levels as well.  At the time of writing, ACPM does not yet have
        a machine-readable conformance report schema or public test corpus
        comparable to those defined for the Autonomous Agent Interchange
        Format; level claims are presently verified by inspection against
        this table rather than by an automated suite.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="relationship-prior-art" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Related Work and Mapping to Prior Art</name>
      <t>
        ACPM's overall design intent parallels the Open Cybersecurity Schema
        Framework: one canonical schema so that disparate parties describe
        the same kind of thing — there, security events; here, agent
        capabilities, trust, cost, and service level — in a comparable way.
      </t>
      <t>
        Three further efforts overlap with ACPM closely enough to warrant
        explicit discussion rather than a one-line table entry. The first is
        <xref target="HACP"/> ("HACP: A Capability-Contract Protocol for AI
        Agents and Edge Hardware"), an active IETF individual submission
        defining a JSON-RPC 2.0 protocol through which an LLM agent
        discovers, plans, executes, observes, and audits operations against
        physical edge hardware (GPIO, I2C, UART, sensors) via a
        security-checked daemon.  Its servers register an immutable tool set
        at startup, each tool carrying a risk level from zero to three, and a
        session is capped at a configured maximum risk level that it
        <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> exceed when executing a tool.  This is the
        same underlying idea ACPM generalizes — declare what a subject can
        do, and at what risk or trust tier, before a consumer relies on it —
        but HACP is narrowly scoped to hardware control, statically declared
        with no dynamic capability negotiation, and organized around risk
        tiers rather than ACPM's combination of trust, cost, service level,
        and delegation.  HACP is cited here as a narrow, complementary
        precedent for capability-contract thinking, not as a competing
        general-purpose effort.
      </t>
      <t>
        The second is a still-forming discovery-metadata effort within the
        Model Context Protocol itself.  The MCP development roadmap
        <xref target="MCP-ROADMAP"/>, as published 2026-03-05, lists under
        "Transport Evolution and Scalability" a planned "MCP Server Cards"
        standard: structured server metadata exposed via a well-known URL so
        that browsers, crawlers, and registries can discover a server's
        capabilities without connecting to it, attributed to a "Server Card
        WG" coordinating with what the roadmap calls "the broader industry
        AI-catalog effort."  This is directly adjacent to an ACPM profile
        with subject_type "platform" or "tool": both are machine-readable,
        well-known-style capability and metadata documents intended for
        discovery without a live connection.  The relevant framing is
        superset and instance, not competition: MCP Server Cards are scoped
        specifically to MCP servers, while ACPM is protocol-agnostic, spans
        agent, platform, tool, and model subjects, and additionally
        expresses cost, service level, trust, and delegation that a server
        card is not designed to carry.  An ACPM profile of subject_type
        "tool" describing an MCP server <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be designed so
        that its capability- and protocol-relevant fields are exportable as,
        or trivially mappable to, a future MCP Server Card.  Because the
        Server Card WG appears to have only just been chartered as of the
        cited roadmap snapshot, this mapping is necessarily provisional; see
        PUBLISHING.md Section 0 for the re-check required before any
        concrete compatibility claim is finalized.
      </t>
      <t>
        The third is the Agent Bill of Materials (AgBOM) concept referenced
        by the OWASP Agent Observability Standard (AOS) project
        <xref target="OWASP-AOS"/>, which proposes inventorying what an
        agent or system is built from — models, tools, dependencies — using
        existing software-supply-chain formats such as CycloneDX, SPDX, and
        SWID.  AgBOM overlaps with ACPM's subject, tools, and models
        inventory fields, but its center of gravity differs: AgBOM concerns
        supply-chain provenance and inventory (what is inside a subject, for
        vulnerability and license tracking), while ACPM concerns runtime
        capability, trust, cost, and service-level declaration (what a
        subject can do, and on what trust and cost terms it can be relied
        upon).  The two are complementary; a profile's subject.sc_refs array
        <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> point at a companion AgBOM document for
        supply-chain detail ACPM itself does not capture.
      </t>
      <t>
        No effort found during this review combines capability support
        level, trust and attestation, cost, service level, and delegation
        rules into a single vendor-neutral document spanning agent,
        platform, tool, and model subjects the way ACPM does.  The closest
        individual pieces — HACP's risk tiers, MCP Server Cards' discovery
        metadata, and AgBOM's inventory model — each cover one facet of this
        narrowly and within a single domain.  What is new in ACPM is the
        combination and its cross-domain generality, not any single
        constituent idea in isolation.
      </t>
      <table align="center">
        <name>Domain-Adjacent Efforts (Informative)</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Effort</th>
            <th align="left">Scope</th>
            <th align="left">Overlap with ACPM</th>
            <th align="left">Relationship</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>HACP (draft-sunyi-hacp-protocol-00)</td>
            <td>JSON-RPC capability-contract protocol for LLM agents controlling physical edge hardware, with static per-session risk-level caps (0-3).</td>
            <td>Capability declaration plus trust/risk-tier gating, similar in spirit to capabilities[] and trust.level.</td>
            <td>Narrow, complementary precedent; hardware-only, no cost/SLA/delegation model.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>MCP Server Cards (planned, MCP roadmap, 2026-03-05)</td>
            <td>Well-known-hosted structured metadata for MCP servers, for discovery without connecting; owned by a newly forming Server Card WG.</td>
            <td>Discovery-oriented capability/metadata document using the same well-known publication pattern as an ACPM tool/platform profile.</td>
            <td>ACPM as superset/general case; Server Cards as the MCP-specific instance. Still forming; re-check before finalizing compatibility claims.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>AgBOM (OWASP Agent Observability Standard project; builds on CycloneDX/SPDX/SWID)</td>
            <td>Supply-chain inventory of what an agent or system is built from, for vulnerability and license tracking.</td>
            <td>Declarative inventory overlap with subject/tools[]/models[].</td>
            <td>Complementary, different center of gravity: AgBOM is provenance, ACPM is runtime offering. sc_refs[] may point at a companion AgBOM document.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Open Container Initiative image manifests</dt>
        <dd>
          An OCI image manifest declares what is actually present in an
          image, not merely what was intended.  ACPM's capability support
          levels (native, emulated, partial, none) apply the same
          "declare what is actually there" discipline to agent capabilities.
        </dd>
        <dt>NIST capability maturity models</dt>
        <dd>
          ACPM's four-level support axis is a simplified maturity assessment
          in the spirit of staged capability maturity frameworks, scoped to
          a single binary-leaning feature rather than an organisational
          process.
        </dd>
        <dt>Cloud provider service catalogs</dt>
        <dd>
          Service catalog listings (for example, marketplace entries for
          managed cloud services) enumerate what a service exposes and its
          operational limits.  ACPM's tools, models, and memory inventories
          serve an analogous purpose for AI agent capabilities.
        </dd>
        <dt>Agent2Agent (A2A) Agent Cards</dt>
        <dd>
          An Agent Card <xref target="A2A"/> is a deliberately minimal
          discovery document advertising identity, capability tags, and an
          endpoint URL.  ACPM
          extends this with an explicit trust, attestation, sandbox, cost,
          and service-level model that an Agent Card does not specify, while
          remaining compatible in spirit with the discovery use case.
        </dd>
        <dt>Model Context Protocol (MCP) capability negotiation</dt>
        <dd>
          MCP <xref target="MCP"/> servers and clients negotiate supported
          capabilities at connection time via an initialize handshake.
          ACPM's tools array is a static, publishable analogue of that
          runtime negotiation, suitable for offline comparison before a
          connection is ever established.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        ACPM is a claims format, not a verification protocol.  Every field in
        a profile <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be treated by a Consumer as a
        self-reported claim by the subject, or by whoever published the
        profile on the subject's behalf, unless the Consumer independently
        verifies it.  This specification does not provide, and does not
        imply, a cryptographic guarantee of any claim's accuracy.
      </t>
      <t>
        A profile <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> declare trust.level "enterprise" with no
        supporting evidence.  A Consumer making a consequential trust
        decision <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> require a verifiable attestation
        (method "third_party" or "formal_audit") with a reachable
        evidence_url and an unexpired attestation.expires_at before relying
        on an "attested" or "enterprise" claim.
      </t>
      <t>
        Capability support claims are asserted, not tested, by this
        specification.  A Consumer performing capability matching for a
        safety-relevant feature <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> independently probe the
        subject before trusting a "native" support claim for that purpose.
      </t>
      <t>
        Cost and service-level claims are point-in-time and unverified.
        ACPM does not currently distinguish a contractually committed figure
        from an observed historical one.  A Consumer making a procurement or
        routing decision of consequence <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> corroborate
        such claims against independent monitoring.
      </t>
      <t>
        The provenance.signature field is advisory.  ACPM does not mandate a
        signature scheme, key-distribution mechanism, or verification
        behaviour.  A Consumer that requires provenance assurance
        <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> treat a profile lacking a signature it can
        independently verify as equivalent to trust.level "untrusted",
        regardless of what trust.level the profile itself declares.
      </t>
      <t>
        A delegation rule naming a Condition language a Consumer does not
        implement <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be treated as unsatisfiable-unknown,
        with a conservative default applied (deny for outbound, reject for
        inbound).  Silently treating an unsupported Condition as satisfied is
        a conformance violation and could permit unintended delegation.
      </t>
      <t>
        Nothing in ACPM cryptographically binds a profile document to the
        real-world subject it claims to describe, beyond the advisory
        subject.sc_refs cross-reference.  A Consumer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
        only trust profiles obtained from a channel it already trusts (the
        subject's own domain, or a registry it already trusts) rather than an
        arbitrary, unauthenticated URL.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
        This document requests no IANA actions.  ACPM's capability
        identifiers (the dot-namespaced strings used in the capabilities
        array) currently form an open, convention-based vocabulary shared
        informally with the Autonomous Agent Interchange Format's
        required-capability vocabulary, with no registry operator.  A future
        revision of this document or an accompanying document may propose a
        community-operated or IANA-operated registry for capability
        identifiers, analogous to the extension registries described for the
        Autonomous Agent Interchange Format, should the vocabulary's growth
        warrant centralised coordination.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>

      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

        <reference anchor="RFC2119"
                   target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119">
          <front>
            <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="1997" month="March"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2119"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC8174"
                   target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc8174">
          <front>
            <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Leiba" fullname="B. Leiba">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="May"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8174"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="JSON-SCHEMA"
                   target="https://json-schema.org/draft/2020-12">
          <front>
            <title>JSON Schema: A Media Type for Describing JSON Documents</title>
            <author initials="A." surname="Wright" fullname="A. Wright">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="H." surname="Andrews" fullname="H. Andrews">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2022"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <reference anchor="SC-006"
                   target="https://github.com/Observalytics-SL/aaif/">
          <front>
            <title>Autonomous Agent Interchange Format (AAIF) — SPECIFICATION</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Schema Commons</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2026"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="MCP"
                   target="https://modelcontextprotocol.io">
          <front>
            <title>Model Context Protocol</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Anthropic</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="A2A"
                   target="https://github.com/a2aproject/A2A">
          <front>
            <title>Agent2Agent Protocol</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Linux Foundation (Agent2Agent Project)</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2025"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="HACP">
          <front>
            <title>HACP: A Capability-Contract Protocol for AI Agents and Edge Hardware</title>
            <author initials="Y." surname="Sun" fullname="Yi Sun">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2026"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-sunyi-hacp-protocol-00"/>
          <format type="TXT" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-sunyi-hacp-protocol/"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="MCP-ROADMAP">
          <front>
            <title>Model Context Protocol Development Roadmap</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Model Context Protocol contributors</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2026" month="March" day="5"/>
          </front>
          <format type="HTML" target="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/development/roadmap"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="OWASP-AOS">
          <front>
            <title>Agent Observability Standard (AOS) — Agent Bill of Materials (AgBOM)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>OWASP</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2026"/>
          </front>
          <format type="HTML" target="https://aos.owasp.org"/>
        </reference>

      </references>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
